Finding Aid for the Arthur Stern papers, 1938-2013 LSC.2332
UCLA Library Special Collections
Arthur Stern papers
1938-2013
LSC.2332
UCLA Library Special Collections
29.4 linear feet (66 boxes, 1 half box, 2 shoeboxes, 2 flat storage boxes, and 1 carton)
Arthur P. Stern (1925-2012) was a Holocaust survivor, engineer, and philanthropist born in Budapest, Hungary. The collection includes his personal and professional papers, such as technical publications, correspondence and printed material from conferences and professional organizations, and company-related correspondence and memos, as well as personal correspondence with family and friends from throughout Stern’s life. The collection also includes correspondence and documentation related to the Holocaust and the Stern family’s efforts for restitution, as well as correspondence and printed materials related to the many community organizations with which Stern was involved.
Stern, Arthur P.
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Stern family; gift; 2017.
General note
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 8147898
Biography/History
Arthur P. Stern was a Holocaust survivor, engineer, and philanthropist born in Budapest, Hungary on July 20, 1925. In 1944, he was deported to the Bergen-Belsen concentration camp as part of the Kasztner transport and was then taken to a refugee camp in Switzerland. After liberation, he studied at the University of Geneva, the University of Lausanne, and the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich (ETH), where he earned a Diplom-Ingenieur and also served as an instructor.
Stern immigrated to the United States in 1951, where he worked for General Electric (GE) in Syracuse, NY and earned his master’s degree in electrical engineering at Syracuse University. At GE, he was involved with pioneering technology for the transistor radio and the color television. He then served as Engineering Director of Martin Marietta’s electronics division and managed the design of defense systems at Bunker Ramo Corporation. Stern became Vice President of the Magnavox Company in 1966. At Magnavox, he led the team that developed the Navstar Global Positioning System. He retired in 1991 as President of Magnavox Advanced Products and Systems and as Vice Chairman of the Magnavox Government and Industrial Electronics Company (MAGIEC). Over the course of his career, Stern authored a number of technical papers and 12 patents, and was involved with numerous professional organizations including the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), of which he served as President in 1975, and the International Solid-State Circuits Conference (ISSCC), of which he was a founder. His work had a lasting impact, as transistor technology and the other solid-state electronics developments that followed paved the way for the chips now found in computers and cell phones.
After his retirement, Stern became active in non-profit and Jewish community organizations, at both a local and national level. He served as Founding President of the California Israel Chamber of Commerce, Vice Chair of Los Angeles Jewish Community Relations Committee, Director of the National Jewish Council for Public Affairs, and Chairman of the California Humanitarian Foundation for Holocaust Survivors.
Stern and his wife, Edith, had three children: Daniel, Jacqueline, and Claude, and seven grandchildren. He died on May 25, 2012 in Beverly Hills, California.
Scope and Content
The papers of Arthur Stern date from 1938-2013 and include material related to both his personal and professional activities. His professional materials begin with notes and papers from his engineering studies in Switzerland. The Engineering series principally includes company-related correspondence, memos, and travel itineraries from his career at General Electric (1951-1961), Martin Marietta (1961-1964), Bunker Ramo Corporation (1964-1966), and Magnavox (1966-1991). The professional materials also include correspondence and printed material related to conferences and professional organizations, particularly the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), which Stern led as President in 1975. Engineering technical publications are included in the Publications series. One strength of the collection is its documentation of patent paperwork and correspondence related to the transistor radio, color television, and GPS systems.
The collection also includes personal correspondence with family and friends from throughout Stern’s life, particularly with his parents Leon and Bertha, his brother Robert, and his children. Much of the correspondence with family who remained in Europe is in German and Hungarian. The personal materials also include legal correspondence and documentation related to the Holocaust and the Stern family’s efforts for restitution. Another strength of the collection is the oral history transcripts and recordings in which Stern discusses his experience of the Holocaust, including an interview with his son, Claude, and an interview with the USC Shoah Foundation.
Additionally, the collection includes correspondence and printed materials related to the many community organizations with which Stern was involved, particularly after his retirement from Magnavox in 1991. Some notable organizations represented in the collection are the California Humanitarian Foundation for Holocaust Survivors, Americans for Peace Now, and the California Israel Chamber of Commerce.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Engineering 1948-2011
Subseries 1.1: Switzerland 1948-1951
Subseries 1.2: Early career 1951-1966
Subseries 1.3: Magnavox 1964-2004
Subseries 1.4: Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) 1972-2011
Series 2: Publications 1953-2004
Series 3: Personal materials 1940-2012
Series 4: Holocaust restitution 1938-2013
Series 5: Community Involvement 1966-2012
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Related Material
Arthur Stern’s oral history with the USC Shoah Foundation is available digitally through the Shoah Foundation’s Visual History Archive.
Stern, Arthur P. -- Archives.; Electronics engineers--United States--Archives.; Holocaust survivors--United States--Archives.
- Series 1: Engineering, 1948-2011
  Scope and Content
  The Engineering series covers Arthur Stern’s professional activity from his education in postwar Switzerland through his retirement from Magnavox in 1991. The series includes memos, company-related correspondence, and business-related travel itineraries. It also includes correspondence, conference materials, and other printed matter related to Stern’s involvement with professional organizations such as the Institute of Radio Engineers (IRE), the Solid-State Circuits Conference (SSSC), and the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE).
  Organization and Arrangement
  The Engineering series is arranged in four subseries which cover his career chronologically, with the exception of the IEEE subseries, which is contemporaneous with the Magnavox subseries.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - Subseries 1.1: Switzerland, 1948-1951
    The Switzerland subseries, 1948-1951, contains handwritten class notes from Arthur Stern’s time as a student at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich (ETH Zurich) and the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Lausanne. It also includes academic papers he wrote on engineering and family law and lecture notes from his tenure as an instructor at ETH. Much of the material is in German and French.
    Materials are arranged chronologically.
    - Student cards and books University of Geneva and University of Lausanne, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Student cards for admission to law school at the University of Geneva, membership card for the Student Association at the University of Lausanne, library card from Lausanne, exam proof from law department at University of Geneva, student notebooks documenting registration for courses at University of Geneva and University of Lausanne.
    - University notebooks, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folders 2-5)
      French materials include: physics notebook, notebook for general physics 2 – electricity from engineering school at University of Lausanne, applied mathematics notebook.
      German materials include: notebook and drawings for electromechanical construction, notebook for theoretical principles of remote control technology, notebook for introduction to remote control technology.
    - Georg Lukacs text, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Essay: “Reification and the Consciousness of the Proletariat” from Georg Lukács’ History and Class Consciousness.
    - Stern essay: "Family and Marriage", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Essay for a civil law course at the University of Geneva’s law school: “Family and marriage.”
    - Transcripts and Translations Swiss Universities, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      German materials include: Documents from Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich on acceptance to and successful completion of a diploma as electrical engineer including course list, ID card as assistant in electrical engineering, general recommendation letter for Stern from Union of Jewish Students, report on the progress of his work as assistant February 1952 (including light engineering, grades, necessary work), graph of light efficiency in cold cathode tube, letter to president of Swiss student’s association to ask for leave to visit USA and statement of his employment, report on current state of light engineering lab and suggestions for future developments, assistant employment contract under Prof. Strutt, recommendations and statements regarding Stern’s position and PhD subject before leaving for USA, release from Institute after deciding to stay in US and related recommendations.
      French materials include: Transcripts from University of Lausanne, exam results from the University of Lausanne.
    - Thesis ETH Zurich, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      A bound copy of thesis on band filters with a frequency response of 1/3 octaves.
    - Stern Article ETH, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Early article written by Stern on the ignition of low pressure discharges.
    - ETH papers and course notes, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Early article written by Stern on the ignition of low pressure discharges, lectures given at the ETH on light engineering including lectures given by Stern on light generation and electric discharge.
    - ETH lectures, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folders 4-7)
      Lecture on the theory of light generation, copy of article on the ignition of low pressure discharges, lecture on gas discharge, bound collection of all lectures given as part of the lecture series on light engineering at the ETH.
    - Lecture notes and Bulletin of Swiss Association of Electrical Engineers, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Article written by Stern on light and lighting technology at the ETH and the university’s developments and contributions, blueprints for a direct current generator and traction generator and related paper discussing its form, construction and function, semester papers on the theoretical basis of telephone engineering and on an introduction to signal engineering.
    - "Einfuhrung in die Lichttechnik" ("Introduction to Light Engineering"), 1951 (Box 3, Folders 2-3)
      "Introduction to Light Engineering," written as part of internship at the electrical engineering institute at the ETH.
    - Diploma, 1948 (Box 72)
  - Subseries 1.2: Early Career, 1951-1966
    The Early Career subseries (1951-1966) covers Stern’s career at General Electric (GE), Martin Marietta, Bunker Ramo Corporation, and his master’s work at Syracuse University. It includes internal company reports, patent paperwork, and company-related correspondence. It also includes printed matter and correspondence related to Stern’s activity with professional organizations during this time period, including the Institute of Radio Engineers (IRE) and the Solid-State Circuits Conference (SSCC).
    - Syracuse and MIT, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lab photographs, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - GE patent paperwork, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folders 6-7)
    - Long internal letters and memoranda, 1953-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Institute of Radio Engineers Convention records, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 3, Folder 9)
    - GE Electronics Division Exempt Salary Administration Plan, 1955 (Box 4, Folders 2-3)
    - "America's Next Twenty Years", 1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Conference programs and reports, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Transistor Circuits Conference Final Report, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - GE Engineering Personnel Register, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - GE Association Island Conference, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - GE Professional Business Management Course, 1956 (Box 5, Folders 1-4)
    - Syracuse University diploma, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - GE Electronics Lab Function Guide, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Institute of Radio Engineers proceedings and publications, 1957-1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - GE Electronics Laboratory publications, 1958-1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - GE internal publications, 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folders 2-3)
    - GE Advanced Management Course, 1959 (Box 6, Folders 4-6)
    - Solid State Circuits Conference, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - MIT bulletin, 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - GE Technical Information Series, 1959-1961 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - GE proposal and progress report, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - GE: "Development of Thin Film Vacuum Deposition Processes and Machinery", 1960 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Solid State Circuit Conference, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - GE Questionnaire on Integrated Electronics, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - GE Company Confidential Integrated Electronic Devices Study (Box 8, Folders 3-4)
    - Technical writings and GE internal publications, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - GE Europe visit, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - GE resignation, 1961 May 16 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Martin ASW business study, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Martin Electronics Division Engineering Five Year Plan: 1961-1965, 1961 August 29 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Martin Marietta internal publications, 1961-1962 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Martin Engineering Design Review, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Martin Marietta Engineering Status and Plans, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Martin Marietta Research Development and Activities, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Martin Marietta News, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bunker Ramo relocation guides, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Bunker Ramo Market Penetration, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Bunker Ramo Programs and Administration Control Forms, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Bunker Ramo report, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Professional awards, 1955-1964 (Box 72)
  - Subseries 1.3: Magnavox, 1964-2004
    The Magnavox subseries covers Stern’s career at Magnavox from 1966-1991 and his professional activity following retirement. It includes company memos and reports, company-related correspondence, travel itineraries and related correspondence, and calendars. Chron files from the 1980s gather company correspondence and memos in chronological order. The subseries also includes correspondence and printed materials related to professional organizations with which he was involved during this time period. Most materials related to the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) from this time period have been kept with the IEEE subseries. As a result, travel itineraries and related correspondence from 1975, when Stern served as IEEE President, are found in the IEEE subseries 1.4.
    Materials are arranged chronologically and by type of material.
    - Arthur Stern resume, circa 1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Arthur Stern professional headshots, 1966, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Magnavox PR, 1964-1985 (Box 10, Folders 1-2)
    - News release: Magnavox corporate vice president, 1973 May 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Security clearance forms, 1965-1983 (Box 10, Folders 4-5)
    - Articles about Arthur Stern, 1966, 1969, 1973, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Magnavox Research Laboratory Operations, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Memos, business correspondence, and company publications, 1966-1990 (Box 10, Folder 8, Box 11, Folders 1-7)
    - Magnavox reports and reviews, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Review of Advanced Product Division, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Magnavox reports, 1973-1991 (Box 12, Folders 3-5)
    - Overseas address list, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence: Professor Ed Gerecke ETH, 1968-1969 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      German materials include: list of dissertations written under Prof. Gerecke and article regarding his retirement summarizing his career and technical contributions, letters of congratulations and the conferral of an honorary doctorate from the Technical University of Darmstadt, ETH bulletins concerning news at the Institute and announcing Gerecke’s resignation
    - Company-related personal correspondence, 1966-1975 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Company-related travel correspondence, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Company-related correspondence, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Company-related correspondence, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Company-related correspondence, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Company-related correspondence, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Security briefings and visit request forms, 1984-1990 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Magnavox Government and Industrial Electronics Company (MAGIEC) correspondence, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Navstar GPS correspondence, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Notes and correspondence on Israel sales consulting, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Company-related correspondence and security clearance documents, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - International correspondence, 1980-1990 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Congressman Glenn Anderson, 1981-1990 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - WM Satellite Company, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Lockerbie incident, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Company-related correspondence, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - The RMS Company correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 15, Folders 1-2, Box 14, Folders 7-8)
    - Company-related correspondence, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Magnavox Christmas gift list, 1976-1990 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Magnavox Christmas party table list, 1977-1989 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Magnavox Christmas liquor list, 1984-1989 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Magnavox employee year-end letters, 1987-1990 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Retirement announcement, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Goodbye letters list, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Retirement congratulations letters, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Chron File, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Chron File, 1984 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Chron File, 1985 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Chron File, 1986 (Box 16, Folders 4-5)
    - Chron File, 1987 (Box 16, Folders 6-7)
    - Chron File, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Chron File, 1989 (Box 17, Folders 2-3)
    - Chron File - Magnavox correspondence, 1989 (Box 17, Folders 4-5)
    - Chron File, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 6, Box 18, Folders 1-2)
    - Chron File - Magnavox correspondence, 1990 (Box 18, Folders 3-5)
    - Engineering professional organizations, 1970-2003 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Club of Rome, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 7, Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Speeches and presentation slides, 1976, 1982, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Membership: National Academy of Engineering, 1977-1978 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Membership: American Association for the Advancement of Science - fellow, 1982-1990 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Institute of Internal Auditors, 1983-1987 (Box 19, Folder 5-7)
    - Jerusalem Economic Conference, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - President's Blue Ribbon Commission on Defense Management, 1986 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - R and D Cooperation Conference, 1987 (Box 20, Folders 3-4)
    - Engineering Advisory Councils: Cal State Long Beach and UC Santa Barbara, 1987-1990 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - CEO Roundtables, 1989-1992 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Pacific CEO Institute Roundtable: Pebble Beach, CA (Inn at Spanish Bay), 1990 November (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Energizing Market Forum, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1992-1997 (Box 21, Folders 2-3)
    - Overseas trip: Israel, Italy, Germany, Switzerland, England, 1969 July-August (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Overseas trip: Japan, Australia, 1970 July-August (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Overseas trip: Europe, 1971 August-September (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Overseas trip: Europe, Israel, 1972 July-August (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Overseas trip: Japan, Hong Kong, Taiwan, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Overseas trip: Europe, 1972 April (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Overseas trip: Europe, 1973 March (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Overseas trip: Europe, 1973 May (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Overseas trip: Europe, 1973 November (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - 1974 trips to Europe, 1973-1974 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Overseas trip: London, Brussels, Copenhagen, Amsterdam, Switzerland, Madrid, 1974 April-May (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Overseas trip: England, Switzerland, Norway, Belgium, 1974 February-March (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Overseas trip: South America and Mexico, 1974 July-August (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Overseas trip: Russia, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Overseas trip: The Netherlands, Switzerland, 1974 December (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Overseas trip: England, Switzerland, the Netherlands, Copenhagen, 1976 February (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Overseas trip: England, Switzerland, Denmark, Sweden, Norway, France, Spain, 1976 May-June (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Overseas trip: England, Switzerland, Holland, Hamburg, Oslo, Denmark, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Overseas trip: Florida, London, Oslo, Copenhagen, the Netherlands, Switzerland, Rome, Paris, 1976 December (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Overseas trip: London, Switzerland, Holland, Hamburg, 1977 February-March (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Overseas trip: England, Holland, Switzerland, France, Norway, Italy, Israel, 1977 April-May (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Overseas trip: Paris, Stockholm, Switzerland, 1977 June (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Overseas trip: Holland, Switzerland, Copenhagen, Oslo, England, Hamburg, Paris, 1977 September-October (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Overseas trip: West Germany, Zurich, Geneva, Amsterdam, 1977 November (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Overseas trip: East Coast United States, England, Switzerland, Holland, France, West Germany, 1978 February-March (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Overseas trip: Tokyo, People's Republic of China, Hong Kong, 1978 May-June (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Overseas trip: England, the Netherlands, France, West Germany, 1978 July-August (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Overseas trip: Genoa, Milan, Copenhagen, Rome, England, Switzerland, Paris, 1978 September (Box 23, Folder 7)